Register of Henryk Piecuch papers, 1920-2012
Hoover Institution Archives
Henryk Piecuch papers
1920-2012
1954-2000
96009
Hoover Institution Archives
19 manuscript boxes, 3 oversize boxes, 1 card file box (10.5 linear feet)
The collection is largely composed of Henryk Piecuch's research materials for his various books as well as his published and unpublished writings. The research materials in the collection span from 1920 to 2012 and focus on Polish Communist intelligence and counterintelligence efforts. Includes photocopies of internal documents of Polish intelligence and security agencies.
Piecuch, Henryk
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1996.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Documents in boxes 15 to 23 form an accrual of the collection donated by Henryk Piecuch in 1996. The accrual has been introduced to the entire collection in September of 2014 under the series title Incremental Materials. The materials represented in the accrual are composed of, correspondence, individual files, Radio Free Europe, research files, Solidarność, writings and related materials, and sound and video recordings. Materials in the accrual are divided into sub-categories mentioned earlier and are an extension of sub-categories created earlier in the year when the collection was initially described and arranged in April of 2014.
Biographical Note
Henryk Piecuch was born December 4th, 1939, in Bielsko-Biała, Poland. After obtaining his military education, for 35 years he served as an officer in the Wojska Ochrony Pogranicza (WOP)(Border Guard) in Poland. Towards the end of the 1960s his military career took a different turn and he started writing articles for the WOP weekly, Granica. Though he started as a field reporter, shortly after 1978 he was promoted to assistant executive editor and later executive editor. Piecuch achieved the rank of colonel and continued in his military duties until 1994, when he retired from both his military and journalist careers. He is a prominent author of 66 books, various articles, stories, and poems. Piecuch's work is primarily focused on Polish Communist intelligence, counterintelligence, and internal security.
Scope and Content of Collection
The collection is largely composed of Henryk Piecuch's research materials for his various books as well as his published and unpublished writings. The research materials in the collection span from 1920 to 2012 and focus on Polish Communist intelligence and counterintelligence efforts. The collection is divided into two series.
The first series is composed of personal files: correspondence, legal materials from cases filed against Piecuch and cases he participated in, memorabilia, as well as his writings and writings of others Piecuch edited. The second series is composed of various research materials that Piecuch used for his publications: intelligence and counterintelligence materials, background files on various individuals associated with or affected by secret service activities in Communist Poland, materials on Radio Wolna Europa (Radio Free Europe), and Solidarność (Solidarity).
Espionage, Polish.; Internal security--Poland.; Secret service--Poland.
- Personal Files, 1954-2012
  Scope and Contents
  Composed of various materials that closely relate to Piecuch on a personal and professional level, the bulk of the documents in this series consist of correspondence, legal materials from court proceedings in which Piecuch was involved, memorabilia, and his various writings and publications.
  - Correspondence, 1973-2002
    Composed of correspondence in the form of letters and e-mails that Piecuch received between 1973-2002. Most letters and e-mails are of professional nature.
    - Letters received, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Letters received, 1993-1999 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Letters received, 2000-2002 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Legal Materials, 1996-2000
    Documents legal proceedings for the Adam Rosenbusch, Piotr i Paweł, and the 1 Samodzielny Batalion Kobiecy im. Emilii Plater cases.
    - Piotr i Paweł, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Rosenbusch, Adam, 1999-2000 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Samodzielny Batalion Kobiecy im. Emilii Plater, 1996-2000 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Samodzielny Batalion Kobiecy im. Emilii Plater, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Memorabilia, 1982-1992
    Composed of various memorabilia related to Piecuch writings. The subseries includes a dedicated and autographed copy of Mieczysław Rakowski book titled, Jak to Się Stało. Additionally, the subseries includes a facsimile of the Martial Law announcement autographed and dedicated to Piecuch by Wojciech Jaruzelski.
    - Jak to Się Stało, 1991 (Oversize-box 14, Folder 1)
    - Obwieszczenie, 1992 (Oversize-box 14, Folder 2)
    - Zaproszenia, 1983-1988 (Oversize-box 14, Folder 3)
    - Zezwolenia, 1982 (Oversize-box 14, Folder 4)
  - Writings and Related Materials, 1954-2012
    Composed of manuscripts, working papers, and various published and unpublished works. Also includes writing by other individuals.
    - Autobiography, circa 1980 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Byłem Gorylem Jaruzelskiego, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Byłem Szpiegiem, 2012 (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
    - Jak Było, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Jak Było - Aneks, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 4-7)
    - Pożoga, circa 1985 (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
    - Pożoga, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Rozdział II-IV, 1954-2001 (Box 3, Folder 4-5)
    - Spotkanie z Fejginem, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Superagenci XX Wieku, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 2-3)
    - Tajna historia mojego życia. Wałęsa i... Kryptonim "Bolek" Wersja 1, circa 2012 (Box 4, Folder 4-5)
    - Tajna historia mojego życia. Wałęsa i... Kryptonim "Bolek", circa 2012 (Box 4, Folder 6-7)
    - Writings by Others, 1988-2009 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Writings by Others "Goleniowski," by Marceli Wieczorek, circa 2009 (Box 5, Folder 2-3)
- Research Materials, 1920-2010
  Composed of research materials that reflect the author's field of interest. Divided into four groups that focus on the Polish Communist intelligence and counterintelligence efforts, interviews and background information on various individuals important to the period, and structure and organization information for Radio Wolna Europa (Radio Free Europe) and Solidarność (Solidarity).
  - Intelligence and Counterintelligence, 1920-2007
    Comprised of various materials focused around the activities of the Polish Communist intelligence and counterintelligence organizations, specifically Ministerstwo Spraw Wewnętrznych (MSW) and Ministerstwo Bezpieczeństwa Publicznego (MBP).
    - Afera Alkoholowa, circa 1990 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Agenci, 1969-1988 (Box 5, Folder 5-6)
    - Artykuły, 1982-2005 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Imperium Zła, circa 1999 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Indeks Nazwisk, 1962 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Materiały Współczesne, 1990-2007 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Ministerstwo Bezpieczeństwa Publicznego - Analiza Gry - USA i Wielka Brytania, 1948-1952 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Ministerstwo Bezpieczeństwa Publicznego - Poznański Czerwiec, 1956 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Ministerstwo Spraw Wewnętrznych - Dokumenty Wewnętrzne, 1926-1990 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Ministerstwo Spraw Wewnętrznych - Poakowskie Podziemie Zbrojne, 1994 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Ministerstwo Spraw Wewnętrznych - Z Dziejów Kontrwywiadu, 1982-1988 (Box 7, Folder 2-3)
    - Polska Zjednoczona Partia Robotnicza, 1954 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Ukraińskie Podziemie Nacjonalistyczne, 1920-1939 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Wojska Ochrony Pogranicza, 1949-1992 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Wojska Ochrony Pogranicza, circa 1992 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Wolność i Niezawisłość, 1954 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Zewnętrzne Uwarunkowanie Rozwoju Wydarzeń, circa 1980 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Individual Files, 1947-2010
    Files are composed of background information, interviews, and research files of various individuals associated with the time period. A number of the individuals were the subjects of Piecuch's writings: Wojciech Jaruzelski, Czesław Kiszczak, Zdzisław Najder, Władysław Pożoga, Józef Światło, and Józef Teliga among others.
    - Cieślikowski, Z., 1994 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Gomułka, Władysław, 1956-1965 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Gotówko, Artur - CD 1-17, 2010 (Box 8, Folder 5-8)
    - Gotówko, Artur - CD 18-27, 2010 (Box 9, Folder 1-2)
    - Humer, Adam, 1988-1989 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Humer, Adam - cz. I-IV, 1988-1989 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Janiszewski i Siwicki, circa 1980 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Jaruzelski, Wojciech, 1985-1997 (Box 10, Folder 1-2)
    - Kiszczak, Czesław, 1979 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Krysiuk, Edmund, 1947-1997 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Kukliński i Bauer, 1956-1988 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Malinowski, Helena i Władysław, 1995 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Najder, Zdzisław, 1988 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Pożoga, Władysław, circa 1980 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Pożoga, Władysław, circa 1980 (contd.) (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Rydz-Śmigły, Edward, 1994-2001 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Światło, Józef, 1985 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Teliga, Józef, 2001-2008 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Wieczorek, Marceli, 1967-1977 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Radio Wolna Europa (Radio Free Europe), 1969-1988
    Documents are largely composed of correspondence, manuals, memoranda and broadcast information regarding Radio Free Europe. Additionally, the subseries includes information regarding Zdzisław Najder, and his activities as chief of the Polish language section of Radio Free Europe.
    - Correspondence, 1969-1987 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Manuals, circa 1988 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Memorandums, 1969-1988 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Najder, Zdzisław, 1959-1988 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Okolnik, 1986-1987 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Programs, 1985-1988 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Schedules, circa 1980 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Transcripts, 1982-1988 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Solidarność (Solidarity), 1980-1994
    Documents the activities of the Solidarity movement through its efforts abroad, international support, financial endowment, and the effects Martial Law in Poland had on the Solidarity efforts.
    - Brussels, 1980-1988 (Box 12, Folder 5-7)
    - Financial Endowment, 1980-1989 (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - International Support, 1980-1994 (Box 13, Folder 1-2)
    - Martial Law, 1981-1983 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Martial Law, Błyskawice, circa 1983 (Box 13, Folder 4)
- Incremental Materials, 1940-2007
  Documents in boxes 15 to 23 form an accrual of the collection donated by Henryk Piecuch in 1996. The accrual has been introduced to the entire collection in September of 2014 under the series title Incremental Materials. The materials represented in the accrual are composed of, correspondence, individual files, Radio Free Europe, research files, Solidarność, writings and related materials, and sound and video recordings. Materials in the accrual are divided into sub-categories mentioned earlier and are an extension of sub-categories created earlier in the year when the collection was initially described and arranged in April of 2014.
  - Correspondence, 1980-2004
    - Letters by Others, 1980-2004 (Text 15: 1)
    - Letters Recevied, 1993-2002 (Text 15: 2)
    - Letters Sent, 1992 (Text 15: 3)
  - Individual Files, 1990-2002
    - Bieliński, Konrad, 1995 (Text 15: 4)
    - Borusiewicz, B., 1995 (Text 15: 5)
    - Bujak, Zbigniew, crica 1990 (Text 15: 6)
    - Charyton, Bogdan and Mull, Stephen, circa 2000 (Text 15: 7)
    - Charyton, Bogdan and Mull, Stephen, crica 2000 (Text 15: 8)
    - Fejgin, Anatol, circa 1990 (Text 15: 9)
    - Gotówko, Artur, 1990 (Text 15: 10)
    - Humer, Adam, circa 1990 (Text 15: 11)
    - Lityński, Jan, 1991 (Text 15: 12)
    - Miller, Leszek, 2002 (Text 15: 13)
    - Pomianowski, 1997 (Text 15: 14)
    - Wieczorek, Marceli, circa 1990 (Text 15: 15)
  - Radio Wolna Europa (Radio Free Europe), 1970-1988
    - Administrative Files, 1970-1981 (Text 16: 1)
    - Photographs: Munich Bombing, February 21st, 1981 (Text 16: 2)
    - Radiowy Tygodnik Monachijski, circa 1980 (Text 16: 3)
    - Stenogramy, 1987-1988 (Text 16: 4)
  - Research Files, 1950-1995
    - Archival Research, crica 1980 (Text 16: 5)
    - Jaruzelski, Wojciech, circa 1980 (Text 16: 6)
    - Jaruzelski, Wojciech, circa 1980 (Text 16: 7)
    - Ministerstwo Spraw Wewnętrznych, Dokumenty Wewnętrzne, 1980-1987 (Text 16: 8)
    - Ministerstwo Spraw Wewnętrznych, Dokumenty Wewnętrzne - Copies of Originals, 1950-1956 (Text 16: 9)
    - Najder, Zdzisław, 1995 (Text 16: 10)
    - Notes, 1996 (Text 16: 11)
    - Pożoga, circa 1988 (Text 16: 12)
    - Pożoga, circa 1988 (Text 17: 1-2)
    - Miscellaneous, 1979-1990 (Text 17: 3)
  - Solidarność (Solidarity), 1982-1996
    - Administrative Files, 1987-1996 (Text 17: 4)
    - Correspondence, 1987 (Text 17: 5)
    - Notatka, 1988 (Text 17: 6)
    - Upoważnienia, 1982 (Text 17: 7)
    - Wypowiedzi, 1990 (Text 17: 8)
  - Writings and Printed Matter, 1940-2007
    - Boczoń, circa 1986 (Text 17: 9)
    - Chaciński, Michael, circa 1980 (Text 17: 10)
    - Czechowicz, Konstanty, circa 1980 (Text 17: 11)
    - "Do Broni,", 1942 (Text 17: 12)
    - "Do czynu, do uderzenia,", circa 1940 (Text 17: 13)
    - "Ekzpertyza" - Zgórniak, Marian, circa 1990 (Text 17: 14)
    - Gaworski, Janusz, circa 1990 (Text 17: 15)
    - Gontarczyk, Piotr, circa 1990 (Text 17: 16)
    - GRU - służba tajna Sztabu Generalnego Federacji Rosyjskiej, circa 1990 (Text 17: 17)
    - Grudzień, 1970 - Przebieg wydarzeń na Wybrzeżu Gdańskim (Text 17: 18)
    - Holzer, Jerzy, circa 1990 (Text 17: 19)
    - Iranek-Osmecki, Kazimierz, circa 1990 (Text 17: 20)
    - Kersten, Krystyna, circa 1990 (Text 17: 21)
    - Krupski, Janusz, circa 1990 (Text 17: 22)
    - Kryptologia w służbie wywiadu, wojska i dyplomacji, 1970 (Text 17: 23)
    - Kwiatkowski, 1984 (Text 18: 1)
    - Librach, Jan, circa 1980 (Text 18: 2)
    - Literatura, 1968 (Text 18: 3)
    - Maciszewski, Jarema, circa 1990 (Text 18: 4)
    - Marszałek Józef Piłsudski - życie i wzór, circa 1990 (Text 18: 5)
    - Martinowa, Halina, circa 1990 (Text 18: 6)
    - Mądry, Janusz, circa 1980 (Text 18: 7)
    - Michałowski - Notatka Biograficzna, circa 1990 (Text 18: 8)
    - Michniewicz, Władysław, 1963 (Text 18: 9)
    - Miliony dolarów dla zagranicznych partii komunistycznych, circa 1990 (Text 18: 10)
    - Mitkiewicz, Leon, circa 1990 (Text 18: 11)
    - Naród Polski Gospodarzem Państwa Polskiego, circa 1980 (Text 18: 12)
    - Niepodległość - miesięcznik polityczny Liberlano-Demokratycznej Partii "Nipodległość", 1987 (Text 18: 13)
    - Notatki, 1984 (Text 18: 14)
    - "Nowa Polska,", 1943 (Text 18: 15)
    - Ocena Bazy Pohitlerowskiej, 1986 (Text 18: 16)
    - "Ochrona Bezpieczeństwa Państwa i Porządku Publicznego w Polsce,", 1944-1988 (Text 18: 17)
    - Oficerowie Drugiej Kategorii, 2007 (Text 18: 18)
    - "Ogniwo,", 1938 (Text 18: 19)
    - Okablowana Tarcza, 1995 (Text 18: 20)
    - Okrągły Stół, circa 1980 (Text 18: 21)
    - Paczkowski, Andrzej, circa 1990 (Text 18: 22)
    - Pantera - Orwid, 1987 (Text 18: 23)
    - Piecuch, Henryk, 1991 (Text 18: 24)
    - "Placówka,", 2002 (Text 18: 25)
    - Płk A. Aftyka, circa 1990 (Text 18: 26)
    - Pobóg-Malinowski, Władysław, circa 1980 (Text 18: 27)
    - Popiełuszko, circa 1990 (Text 19: 1)
    - Pożoga, 1968 (Text 19: 2)
    - Rękopis Dzienników dot. Wydarzeń Grudniowych, circa 1990 (Text 19: 3)
    - Rosenbusch, Adam, circa 1990 (Text 19: 4)
    - Rosoh, X. "Dywersja Ideologiczna Przeciwko Polsce w 1984 roku", circa 1980 (Text 19: 5)
    - Rosyjskie służby na starych ścieżkach?, 1992 (Text 19: 6)
    - Samodzielny Batalion Kobiecy im. Emili Platter, circa 1990 (Text 19: 7)
    - Schaff, Adam, "Kopiec Kuklińskiego,", 1997 (Text 19: 8)
    - Skoruszewski, Olgierd, crica 1980 (Text 19: 9)
    - Słowikowski, M., circa 1980 (Text 19: 10)
    - "Służby specjalne i struktury bezpieczeństwa w Polsce, Czechach i na Węgrzech. Wysiłki na rzecz reform i braki u nowych członków NATO,", circa 1990 (Text 19: 11)
    - Solidarność Walcząca, 1994 (Text 19: 12)
    - Sowiński, Ignacy Loga "Nie ma dymu bez ognia,", 1979 (Text 19: 13)
    - Sprawa Alfreda Jaroszewicza, circa 1990 (Text 19: 14)
    - Szczyty, nie szczeble, 2004 (Text 19: 15)
    - Szlachcic, Franciszek, 1988 (Text 19: 16)
    - Szymański, A., circa 1980 (Text 19: 17)
    - "Technologia otrzymywania paliw płynnych, koksu, i lepiszczy elektrodowych oraz sorbentów węglowych z półproduktów uwodornienia węgla,", 1993 (Text 19: 18)
    - "Tezy do Analizy Działań Służb Specjalnych III RP,", circa 1990 (Text 19: 19)
    - "To ja zabiłem ci ojca,", 1999 (Text 19: 20)
    - Werblan, Andrzej, circa 1990 (Text 20: 1)
    - Węzłowe Problemy bezpieczeństwa państwa, 1984 (Text 20: 2)
    - Wiatr, Jerzy, 1944 (Text 20: 3)
    - Wstępna Instrukcja w Sprawie Tymczasowej Organizacji Obozów Pracy, 1977 (Text 20: 5)
    - "Wymarsze,", circa 1980 (Text 20: 6)
    - Zbigniew Brzeziński, nazwisko Utrwalone w Historii - Praca licencjacka, 2006 (Text 20: 7)
    - Złośliwa Dyskredytacja Wojskowych Służb Informacyjnych, 2007 (Text 20: 8)
    - Żywia, i Bronia, 1989 (Text 20: 9)
  - Sound and Video Recordings, 1980-2000
    - Charyton - VHS, crica 1990 (Text 20: 10)
    - Gotówko CD's, circa 2000 (Text 20: 11)
    - Interviews, Lectures, and Radio Broadcasts, 1980-1995 (Boxes 21-22)
      Recordings include interviews with: Fejgin, Jaruzelski, Światło, Najder, Rosenbusch, Charyton, Wieczorek, Kukliński, Staniszewski, Bochański, Bień, and Pożoga.
- Incremental Materials, 2015
  - Electronic file (Box 23)
    Comprised of electornic media such as 3.5 floppy disks, CD-Rs, and a hard drive.